You know, when Video Arts asked me
if I'd like to talk about creativity
I said "no problem!"
No problem!
Because telling people how
to be creative is easy,
it's only being it that's difficult.
I knew it would be particularly
easy for me because I've
spent the last 25 years watching
how various creative people
produce their stuff, and being
fascinating to see if I could
figure out what makes folk,
including me, more creative.
What is more, a couple of
years ago I got very excited
because a friend of mine
who runs the psychology
department at Sussex University,
Brian Bates, showed
me some research on
creativity done at Berkley
in the 70s by a brilliant
psychologist called Donald
MacKinnon which seemed
to confirm in the most
impressively scientific way
all the vague observations
and intuitions that I'd
had over the years.
The prospect of settling down for quite
serious study of creativity for the
purpose of tonight's gossip was delightful.
Having spent several weeks
on it, I can state categorically
that what I have to tell you tonight
about how you can all become more
creative is a complete waste of time.
So I think it would be much better
if I just told jokes instead.
You know the lightbulb jokes?
How many Poles does it
take to screw in a lightbulb?
One to hold the bulb,
four to turn the table.
How many folksingers does
it take to change a lightbulb?
Answer: five, one to
change the bulb and four to
sing about how much better
the old one was. How many
socialists does it take
to change a lightbulb?
Answer: We're not going to
change it, we think it works.
How many creative art
The reason why it is futile
for me to talk about
creativity is that it simply
cannot be explained, it's
like Mozart's music or Van
Gogh's painting or Saddam
Hussein's propaganda. It
is literally inexplicable.
Freud, who analyzed practically
everything else, repeatedly denied that
psychoanalysis could
shed any light
whatsoever
on the mysteries of creativity.
And Brian Bates wrote to me recently
"Most of the best research on creativity
was done in the 60s and 70s with a
quite dramatic drop-off in quantity
after then," largely, I suspect because
researchers began to feel that
they had reached the limits of what
science could discover about it.
In fact, the only thing
from the research that I
could tell you about how
to be creative is the sort
of childhood that you should
have had, which is of
limited help to you at
this point in your lives.
However there is
one negative thing
that I can say
and it's "negative" because it is easier
to say what creativity isn't.
A bit like the sculptor
who when asked how he had
sculpted a very fine elephant,
explained that he'd
taken a big block of marble
and then knocked away
all the bits that didn't
look like an elephant.
Now here's the negative thing:
Creativity is not a talent.
It is not a talent,
it is a way of operating.
So how many actors does it
take to screw in a lightbulb?
Answer: thousands. Only one to do it but
thousands to say "I could have done that."
How many Jewish mothers does it
take to screw in a lightbulb?
Answer: Don't mind me, I'll just sit here
in the dark, nobody cares about…
How many surgeons
You see when I say "a way of
operating" what I mean is this:
creativity is not an ability that
you either have or do not have.
It is, for example, (and this may
surprise you) absolutely unrelated to IQ
(provided that you are intelligent
above a certain minimal
level that is) but MacKinnon
showed in investigating
scientists, architects,
engineers, and writers
that those regarded by
their peers as "most
creative" were in no way
whatsoever different
in IQ from their less
creative colleagues.
So in what way were they different?
MacKinnon showed that the
most creative had simply
acquired a facility for
getting themselves into
a particular mood
"a wayof operating"
which allowed their natural
creativity to function.
In fact, MacKinnon described this
particular facility as an ability to play.
Indeed he described the most creative
(when in this mood) as being childlike.
For they were able to play with
ideas… to explore them…
not for any immediate practical
purpose but just for enjoyment.
Play for its own sake.
Now, about this mood.
I'm working at the moment with Dr.
Robin Skynner
on a successor to our psychiatry book
Families and How To Survive Them we're
comparing the ways in which psychologically
healthy families function (the ways in
which such families function) with the
ways in which the most successful
corporations and organizations function.
We've become fascinated by the fact
that we can usually describe the way
in which people function at work in
terms of two modes: open and closed.
So what i can just add now
is that creativity is not
possible in the closed mode.
So how many American network TV executives
does it take to screw in a lightbulb?
Answer: Does it have to be a lightbulb?
How many doorke...
Let me explain a little. By
the "closed mode" I mean the
mode that we are in most of the
time when  at work.
We have inside us a feeling
that there's lots to be done
and we have to get on with it if
we're going to get through it all.
It's an active (probably
slightly anxious) mode,
although the anxiety can be
exiting and pleasurable.
It's a mode which we're probably a little
impatient, if only with ourselves.
It has a little tension
in it, not much humor.
It's a mode in which we're very
purposeful, and it's a mode in which
we can get very stressed
and even a bit manic,
but not
creative.
By contrast, the open mode, is relaxed…
expansive…
less purposeful mode…
in which we're probably
more contemplative,
more inclined to humor (which always
accompanies a wider perspective)
and, consequently, more playful.
It's a mood in which curiosity
for its own sake can operate
because we're not under pressure to get a
specific thing done quickly. We can play,
and that is what allows our
natural creativity to surface.
Let me give you and example of what I mean.
When Alexander Fleming had
the thought that led to the
discovery of penicillin, he must
have been in the open mode.
The previous day, he'd
arranged a number of
dishes to that culture
would grow upon them.
On the day in question, he
glanced at the dishes, and he
discovered that on one of
them no culture had appeared.
Now, if he'd been in the closed
mode he would have been so
focused upon his need for "dishes
with cultures grown upon them"
that when he saw that one
dish was of no use to him for
that purpose he would quite
simply have thrown it away.
Thank goodness, he was in
the open mode so he became
curious about why the culture
had not grown on this
particular dish. And that
curiosity, as the world knows,
led him to the lightbulb ---
I'm sorry, to penicillin.
Now in the closed mode an
uncultured dish is an irrelevance.
In the open mode, it's a clue.
Now, one more example:
one of Alfred Hitchcock's
regular co-writers
has described working
with him on screenplays.
He says,
"When we came up against a
block and our discussions
became very heated and intense,
Hitchcock would suddenly
stop and tell a story that
had nothing to do with the
work at hand. At first, I was
almost outraged, and then I
discovered that he did this intentionally.
He mistrusted
working under pressure. He would
say "We're pressing, we're
pressing, we're working too hard.
Relax, it will come."
And, says the writer, of
course it finally always did.
But let me make one thing quite clear: we
need to be in the open mode when we're
pondering a problem but
once we come up with a solution,
we must then switch to the
closed mode to implement it.
Because once
we've made a decision,
we are efficient only
if we go through
with it decisively,
undistracted by doubts
about its correctness.
For example, if you decide to leap
a ravine, the moment just before
take-off is a bad time to start
reviewing alternative strategies.
When you're attacking a machine-gun
post you should not make a
particular effort to see the funny
side of what you are doing.
Humor is a natural concomitant in the open
mode, but it's a luxury in the closed .
No, once we've taken a decision
we should narrow our focus
while we're implementing it,
and then after it's been
carried out we should once
again switch back to the open
mode to review the feedback
rising from our action,
in order to decide whether the
course that we have taken
is successful, or whether
we should continue with
the next stage of our plan.
Whether we should create
an alternative plan to correct
any error we perceive.
And then back into the closed mode to
implement that next stage, and so on.
In other words, to be at our
most efficient we need to be
able to switch backwards and
forwards between the two modes.
But here's the problem:
we too often get stuck
in the closed mode.
Under the pressures which are all too
familiar to us we tend to maintain tunnel
vision at times when we really need to
step back and contemplate the wider view.
This is particularly true, for example,
of politicians. The main complaint about
them from their non-political colleagues
is that they become so addicted to the
adrenaline that they get from reacting to
events on an hour-by-hour basis that they
almost completely lose
the desire or the
ability to ponder problems
in the open mode.
So, as I say, creativity is not
possible in the closed mode.
And that's it.
Well… 20 minutes to go… So, how many
women's libbers does it take to change
a lightbulb? Answer: 37, one to screw it
in, and 36 to make a documentary about it.
How many psychiatrists does it take to
change a lightbulb? The answer: only one,
but the lightbulb has
really got to want to change.
Oh, there is one, just one, other thing
that I can say about creativity.
There are certain conditions
which do make it more likely
that you'll get into the
open mode, and that something
creative will occur.
More likely… you can't guarantee
anything will occur. You might
sit around for hours as I did
last Tuesday, and nothing.
Zilch.
Bupkis.
Not a sausage.
Nevertheless I can at
least tell you how to get
yourselves into the open mode.
You need five things:
One
Space
Two
Time
Three
Four
Confidence
Five
a 22 inch waist
Sorry, my mind was wondering.
I'm getting into the
open mode too quickly.
Instead of a 22 inch waist, you need humor.
I do beg your pardon.
Let's take space first:
you can't become playful and therefore
creative if you're under your usual
pressures, because to cope with them
you've got to be in the closed mode.
So you have to create
some space for yourself
away from those demands.
And that means sealing yourself off.
You must make a quiet space for
yourself where you will be undisturbed.
Next: Time. It's not enough
to create space, you have to
create your space for a specific
period of time. You have to
know that your space will last
until exactly (say) 3:30,
and that at that moment your
normal life will start again.
And it's only by having a
specific moment when your
space starts and an equally
space stops that you can seal
yourself off from the every
day closed mode in which
we all habitually operate.
And I'd never realized how vital
this was until I read a historical
study of play by a Dutch
historian called Johan Huizinga
and in it he says "Play is
distinct from ordinary life,
both as to locality and duration.
This is its main characteristic:
its secludedness, its limitedness.
Play begins and then (at
a certain moment) it is over.
Otherwise, it's not play."
So combining the first two factors
we create an "oasis of quiet"
for ourselves by setting the
boundaries of space and of time.
Now creativity can happen,
because play is possible when we
are separate from everyday life.
So, you've arranged to take no calls,
you've closed your door, you've
sat down somewhere comfortable,
take a couple of deep breaths
and if you're anything like me,
after you've pondered some
problem that you want
to turn into an opportunity
for about 90 seconds,
you find yourself thinking "Oh I forgot
I've got to call Jim…
oh, and I must tell Tina
that I need the report
on Wednesday and not
Thursday which means
I must move my lunch with Joe and Damn!
I haven't called St. Paul's about
getting Joe's daughter an interview
and I must pop out this afternoon to
get Will's birthday present and those
plants need watering and none of my
pencils are sharpened and Right! I've
got too much to do, so I'm going to
start by sorting out my paper clips and
then I shall make 27 phone calls and
I'll do some thinking tomorrow when
I've got everything out of the way."
Because, as we all know, it's easier
to do trivial things that are urgent
than it is to do important things
that are not urgent, like thinking.
And it's also easier to do
little things we know we can do,
than to start on big things
that we're not so sure about.
So when I say create
an oasis of quiet
know that when you
have, your mind
will pretty soon
start racing again.
But you're not going
to take that very seriously,
you just sit there
(for a bit) tolerating
the racing and the slight
anxiety that comes with that,
and after a
time your mind will quiet down again.
Now,
because it takes some time for
your mind to quiet down
it's absolutely no use arranging a
"space/time oasis"
lasting 30 minutes, because
just as you're getting quieter
and getting into the open mode
you have to stop and that is
very deeply frustrating. So
you must allow yourself
a good chunk of time. I'd suggest
about an hour and a half.
Then after you've gotten
to the open mode,
you'll have about an hour
left for something to happen,
if you're lucky.
But
don't put a whole morning aside.
My experience is
that after about
an hour-and-a-half
you need a break.
So it's far better to do
an hour-and-a-half
now and then an hour-and-a-half next
Thursday and maybe an hour-and-a-half
the week after that,
than to fix one four-and-a-half
hour session now.
There's another
reason for that,
and that's factor number three:
time.
Yes, I know we've
just done time, but
that was half of
creating our oasis.
Now I'm going to tell you
about how to use the oasis
that you've created.
Why do you still need time?
Well,
let me tell you a story.
I was always intrigued
that one of my Monty Python
colleagues who seemed to be
(to me) more talented than
I was  did never
produce scripts as original as mine.
And I watched for some time
and then I began to see why.
If he was faced with a
problem,
and fairly soon saw a solution,
he was inclined to take it.
Even though (I think) he knew the
solution was not very original.
Whereas if I was in the same situation,
although I was sorely tempted to
take the easy way out, and finish by
5 o'clock,
I just couldn't. I'd sit there
with the problem for another
hour-and-a-quarter, and by sticking at it
would, in the end, almost always come
up with something more original.
It was that simple.
My work was more
creative than his
simply because I was prepared to stick
with the problem longer.
So imagine my excitement
when I found that this was exactly
what MacKinnon found in his research.
He discovered that the most creative
professionals always played with a problem
for much longer before
they tried to resolve it,
because they were
prepared to tolerate
that slight discomfort
and anxiety that we all
experience when we haven't
solved a problem.
You know I mean, if we
have a problem
and we need to solve it, until we do,
we feel (inside us) a kind
of internal agitation,
a tension, or an uncertainty that
makes us just plain uncomfortable.
And we want to get rid
of that discomfort.
So, in order to do so, we
take a decision.
Not because we're sure
it's the best decision,
but because taking it
will make us feel better.
Well,
the most creative
people have learned to
tolerate that discomfort
for much longer.
And so, just because they
put in more pondering
time, their solutions
are more creative.
Now the people I find it hardest
to be creative with are
people who need all the time to project
an image of themselves as decisive.
And who feel that to create
this image they need to decide
everything very quickly and with
a great show of confidence.
Well, this behavior I
suggest sincerely,
is the most effective way of strangling
creativity at birth.
But please note I'm not arguing
against real decisiveness.
I'm 100% in favor of
taking a decision
when it has to be taken
and then sticking to it while
it is being implemented.
What I am suggesting to you is
that before you take a decision,
you should always ask
yourself the question,
"When does this decision
have to be taken?"
And having answered that, you defer the
decision until then,
in order to give yourself
maximum pondering time,
which will lead you to the
most creative solution.
And if, while you're pondering,
somebody accuses you
of indecision say,
"Look, Babycakes,
I don't have to
decide 'til Tuesday,
and I'm not chickening out
of my creative discomfort by
taking a snap decision before
then, that's too easy."
So, to summarize: the third factor
that facilitates creativity is time,
giving your mind as long as possible
to come up with something original.
Now the next factor,
number 4, is
confidence.
When you are in your space/time
oasis, getting into the open mode,
nothing will stop
you being creative
so effectively as the
fear of making a mistake.
Now if you think about
play, you'll see why.
To play is experiment:
"What happens if I do this?
What would happen if we did that?
What if…?"
The very essence of playfulness
is an openness to anything
that may happen. The feeling that
whatever happens, it's ok.
So you cannot be playful if you're
frightened that moving
in some direction
will be "wrong" --
something you
"shouldn't have done."
Well, you're either free
to play, or you're not.
As Alan Watts puts it, you can't
be spontaneous within reason.
So you've got risk saying things
that are silly and illogical
and wrong, and the best way to get the
confidence to do that is to know
that while you're being creative,
nothing is wrong.
There's no such thing
as a mistake,
and any drivel may lead
to the break-through.
And now,
the last factor, the fifth: humor.
Well, I happen to think the
main evolutionary significance
of humor is that it gets
us from the closed mode
to the open mode quicker
than anything else.
I think we all know that
laughter brings relaxation,
and that humor makes us playful,
yet how many times important discussions
been held
where really original
and creative ideas were
desperately needed to
solve important problems,
but where humor was taboo because
the subject being discussed was
"so serious"?
This attitude seems to me
to stem from a very basic
misunderstanding of the difference
between 'serious' and 'solemn'.
Now I suggest to you that
a group of us could be sitting
around after dinner,
discussing matters that
were extremely serious
like the education of
our children,
or our marriages, or
the meaning of life
(and I'm not talking about the
film), and we could be laughing,
and that would not make what we were
discussing one bit less serious.
Solemnity, on the other hand… I
don't know what it's for.
I mean, what is the point of it?
The two most beautiful memorial
services that I've ever attended
both had a lot of humor, and
it somehow freed us all,
and made the services
inspiring and cathartic.
But solemnity? It
serves pomposity,
and the self-important
always know with some
level of their
consciousness that their
egotism is going to be
punctured by humor --
that's why they see
it as a threat. And so
dishonestly pretend
that their deficiency
makes their views
more substantial,
when it only makes
them feel bigger.
No, humor is an essential
part of spontaneity,
an essential part of
playfulness,
an essential part of the
creativity that we need to
solve problems, no matter
how 'serious' they may be.
So when you set up a space/time
oasis, giggle all you want.
And there, ladies and
gentlemen, are the five factors
which you can arrange to make
your lives more creative:
Space, time, time, confidence,
and Lord Jeffrey Archer.
So,
now you know how to get into the
open mode, the only other requirement
is that you keep mind
gently 'round the subject
you're pondering.
You'll daydream, of course, but you
just keep bringing your mind back,
just like with meditation.
Because, and this is the extraordinary
thing about creativity,
if you just keep your mind resting
against the subject in a friendly
but persistent way, sooner or
later
you will get a reward
from your unconscious,
probably in the shower later.
Or at breakfast the next morning,
but suddenly you are rewarded,
out of the blue a new
thought mysteriously appears.
If
you've put in the pondering time first.
So, how many Cecil Parkinsons does it take
to change a lightbulb?
Answer: two, one to screw
it in, one to screw it up.
How many
account executives does it
take to screw in a lightbulb?
Answer: Can I get
back to you on that?
How many Norwei--- Oh, sorry,
how many Yugoslav---
how many Malt--
how many Dutch---
I'm out of jokes.
Oh! One thing!
Looking at you all reminds me,
I think it's easy to be creative if
you've got other people to play with.
I always find that if two (or more) of us
throw ideas backwards and forwards
I get to more interesting
and original places
than I could have ever
have gotten to on my own.
But there is a danger,
a real danger,
if there's one person around you
who makes you feel
defensive,
you lose the confidence to play,
and it's goodbye creativity.
So always make sure your play friends
are people that you like and trust.
And never say anything
to squash them either,
never say "no" or "wrong"
or "I don't like that."
Always be positive, and build
on what is being said:
"Would it be even better if…"
"I don't quite understand that,
can you just explain it again?"
"Go on…"
"What if…?"
"Let's pretend…"
Try to establish as free
an atmosphere as possible.
Sometimes I wonder if the
success of the Japanese
isn't partly due to their
instinctive understanding
of how to use groups creatively.
Westerners are often amazed at the
unstructured nature of Japanese meetings
but maybe it's just
that very lack of structure,
that absence of time pressure, that frees
them to solve problems so creatively.
And how clever
of the Japanese sometimes to
plan that un-structured-ness by,
for example,
insisting that the first people to give
their views are the most junior,
so that they can speak freely
without the possibility
of contradicting what's
already been said by
somebody more important.
Four minutes left…
How many Irish-- sorry, sorry
Well, look, the very last
thing that I can say about
creativity is this: it's like humor.
In a joke, the laugh comes
at a moment
when you connect two different
frameworks of reference in a new way.
Example: there's the
old story about
a woman doing a survey
into sexual attitudes who
stops an airline pilot
and asks him, amongst
other things, when he last
had sexual intercourse.
He replies "Nineteen fifty eight."
Now, knowing airline pilots, the
researcher is surprised, and queries this.
"Well," says the pilot,
"it's only twenty-one ten now."
We laugh, eventually,
at the moment
of contact between two
frameworks of reference:
the way we express what
year it is and the 24-hour clock.
Now, having an idea, a new idea, is
exactly the same thing.
It's connecting two
hitherto separate ideas
in a way that generates
new meaning.
Now,
connecting different ideas isn't difficult,
you can connect cheese with motorcycles
or moral courage with light green, or
bananas with international cooperation.
You can get any computer to make a billion
random connection for you, but
these new connections
or juxtapositions are
significant only
if they generate new meaning.
So as you play you can deliberately try
inventing these random juxtapositions,
and then use your intuition to tell
you whether any of them seem to have
significance for you. That's
the bit the computer can't do.
It can produce millions
of new connections, but
it can't tell which one
smells interesting.
And, of course, you'll
produce some juxtapositions
which are absolutely
ridiculous, absurd.
Good for you!
Because Edward de Bono (who invented
the notion of lateral thinking)
specifically suggests in his book
PO: Beyond Yes and No
that you can try loosening up your
assumptions
by playing with deliberately
crazy connections.
He calls such absurd ideas
"Intermediate Impossibles."
And he points out the
use of an Intermediate
Impossible is
completely contrary
to ordinary logical thinking in which
you have to be right at each stage.
It doesn't matter
if the Intermediate Impossible is right or
absurd, it can nevertheless be used as a
stepping stone to another
idea that is right.
Another example of how, when you're
playing, nothing is wrong.
So, to summarize: if you
really don't know how to
start, or if you got stuck,
start generating random connections,
and allow your intuition
to tell you if one might
lead somewhere interesting.
Well, that
really is all I can tell you that won't
help you to be creative. Everything.
And now, in the
two minutes left,
I can come to the important part,
and that is,
how to stop your subordinates  becoming
creative too, which is the real threat.
Because, believe me no one
appreciates better than I do
what trouble
creative people are.
And how they stop decisive,
hard-nosed bastards
like us from running
businesses efficiently.
I mean, we all know,
we encourage someone
to be creative,
the next thing is
they're rocking
the boat, coming up with
ideas, and asking us
questions. Now if we don't nip
this kind of thing in the bud,
we'll have to start justifying our
decisions by reasoned argument.
And
sharing information -- the
concealment of which gives us
considerable advantages
in our power struggles.
So,
here's how to stamp out creativity
in the rest of the organization
and get a bit of respect going.
One: Allow subordinates no humor, it
threatens your self-importance and
especially your omniscience. Treat all
humor as frivolous or subversive.
Because subversive is, of course,
what humor will be in your setup,
as it's the only way that people
can express their opposition,
since (if they express it openly) you're
down on them like a ton of bricks.
So let's get this clear: blame
humor for the resistance
that your way of working creates.
Then you don't have to blame your
way of working. This is important.
And I mean that solemnly. Your
dignity is no laughing matter. Second:
keeping ourselves
feeling irreplaceable
involves cutting everybody
else down to size,
so don't miss an opportunity to
undermine your employees' confidence.
A perfect opportunity comes when
you're reviewing work that they've done.
Use your authority to zero in immediately
on all the things you can find wrong.
Never never balance the
negatives with positives,
only criticize, just as
your school teachers did.
Always remember: praise
makes people uppity.
Third: Demand that people
should always be actively
doing things. If you
catch anyone pondering,
accuse them of laziness
and/or indecision.
This is to starve employees of
thinking time because that leads to
creativity and insurrection.
So
demand urgency at all times, use
lots of fighting talk
and war analogies, and establish
a permanent atmosphere
of stress, of breathless
anxiety, and crisis.
In a phrase: keep that mode closed.
In this way we no-nonsense types
can be sure that the tiny, tiny,
microscopic quantity of creativity in
our organization will all be ours!
But!
Let your vigilance slip
for one moment, and
you could find yourself
surrounded by happy,
enthusiastic, and creative
people whom you might
never be able to completely
control ever again!
So be careful.
Thank you, and good night. Thank you.